Guide to the David Loeb Weiss Film Collection FILMS.002
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
David Loeb Weiss Film Collection
circa 1967-2023
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Weiss, David Loeb
Sluchansky, Steven
FILMS.002
38 Linear Feet in 35 record cartons and 14 film cans
35 film reels
32 sound tape reels
1 audiocassette
David Loeb Weiss (c. 1911–2005) was a Polish American socialist activist and filmmaker. The David Loeb Weiss Film Collection contains unedited materials, selects, out-takes, trims, and preservation elements from films across Loeb Weiss' career. Users should be aware that one film's title contains a racial slur, which is a direct quote from a protester depicted in the film. The original language has been maintained in archival description to convey the meaning and historical context of the statement. The films in this collection include Profile of a Peace Parade (1967), No Vietnamese Ever Called Me Nigger (1968), To Make a Revolution (1972), Farewell, Etaoin Shrdlu (1980), and Planet Without a Visa (earlier titled I Stake My Life), an uncompleted documentary film about Leon Trotsky. The collection also includes amateur footage of Mountain Spring Camp, a Socialist Workers Party summer resort.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by David Loeb Weiss in 2002. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2002.020 and NPA.2002.044.
An additional gift was donated by Steven Sluchanksy in 2003. The accession number associated with this gift is 2003.053.
Preservation elements for Farewell, Eation Shrdlu created in 2023 for a National Film Preservation Foundation grant project are associated with accession number 2024.002.
Arrangement
Arranged into two series: Series I. Farewell, Etaoin Shrdlu and Series II. Planet Without a Visa. Materials are arranged alpabetically. A majority of the collection has not been arranged or described by an archivist.
Biographical Note
David Loeb Weiss (c. 1911–2005) was a Polish American socialist activist and filmmaker. He received a B.A. in economics from New York University and an M.A. in political science from the New School for Social Research.
Loeb Weiss held a variety of jobs over his lifetime, including a radarman in the U.S. Army, merchant marine, restaurant waiter, farmhand, shipyard worker, busboy, electrician, proofreader for the New York Times, film editor at the United Nations, and leader during the Dura Steel strike in Los Angeles.
Loeb Weiss co-founded the Socialist Workers Party in 1938. In the 1940s, he co-directed the Mountain Spring Camp, a Socialist Workers Party summer resort, and gave lectures at the New York Marxist Labor School. He ran for office on the Socialist Workers Party ticket, including for Mayor of New York City in 1953 and for Governor of New York in 1954.
Over the course of his career as a filmmaker, Loeb Weiss produced and directed five documentary films: Profile of a Peace Parade (1967), No Vietnamese Ever Called Me Nigger (1968), 'Ey Michelangelo (1971), To Make a Revolution (1972), and Farewell, Etaoin Shrdlu (1980).
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Some audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Scope and Contents
The David Loeb Weiss Film Collection contains unedited materials, selects, out-takes, trims, audio recordings, and preservation elements from four of Loeb Weiss' completed films, as well as one incomplete film. Users should be aware that one film's title contains a racial slur, which is a direct quote from a protester depicted in the film. The original language has been maintained in archival description to convey the meaning and historical context of the statement. The films in this collection include:
Profile of a Peace Parade (1967), a documentary about a Times Square parade that took place on Hiroshima Day, protesting the detonation of atom bombs on Nagasaki and Hiroshima
No Vietnamese Ever Called Me Nigger (1968), a portrait of Black anti-war protestors and veterans, filmed during a 1967 march from Harlem to the United Nations
To Make a Revolution (1972), a documentary about the Young Socialist Alliance that depicts its 1970 Convention in New York City
Farewell, Etaoin Shrdlu (1980), a documentary by David Loeb Weiss and Carl Schlesinger showcasing the linotype printing process at The New York Times on the last day that it was used
and Planet Without a Visa (previously titled I Stake My Life), an incomplete documentary film about Leon Trotsky, with Betacam SP transfers.
The collection also includes amateur footage of Mountain Spring Camp, a Socialist Workers Party summer resort co-directed by Loeb Weiss.
World War, 1939-1945 -- Public opinion; Anti-war demonstrations -- United States -- 21st century; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Protest movements -- United States.; Socialists -- New York (State) -- New York.; Socialists -- United States.; American newspapers -- New York (State) -- New York.; Typography; Linotype; Documentary films; Weiss, David Loeb; Sluchansky, Steven; New York Times Company; Socialist Workers Party; Trotsky, Leon, 1879-1940
- Series I. Farewell, Etaoin Shrdlu, 1978-2023; 2 Linear Feet in two record cartons; 31 film reels; 9 sound tape reels; 1 audiocassette
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Farewell, Etaoin Shrdlu includes a dye print, narration and sound elements, trims and outs, preservation elements, a digital scan, and reference materials for the 1980 documentary by David Loeb Weiss and Carl Schlesinger. Farewell showcases the linotype printing process at The New York Times on the last day that it was used.
  - Automation and You at the N.Y. Times, circa 1980 (Box 17, 16mm film reels 002_0009)
  - Digital scan, 1980; cuid43075
    This digital copy of the film was created with duplicate negatives and optical track negatives by vendor BB Optics as part of a National Film Preservation Foundation grant project. The Museum of Modern Art lent the original negative A- and B-rolls and optical track negatives to NYU for this project.
  - Dye print, circa 1980 (Box 17, 16mm film reels 002_0008)
  - Film audio, circa 1980 (Box 34, Audiocassette 002_0029, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0033)
  - Narration, November 18, 1980 (Box 17, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0007, 16mm magnetic full coat rolls 002_0070)
  - Preservation elements, 2023
    - Color interpositive, cuid43068 (Film canister 002_0001, 16mm film reels 002_0001)
    - Color duplicate negative, cuid43069 (Film canister 002_0002, 16mm film reels 002_0002)
    - Optical track negative, cuid43070 (Film canister 002_0003, 16mm film reels 002_0003)
    - Sound answer print, cuid43072 (Film canister 002_0004, 16mm film reels 002_0004)
    - Sound check print, cuid43071 (Film canister 002_0005, 16mm film reels 002_0005)
    - Sound release print, cuid43073 (Film canister 002_0006, 16mm film reels 002_0006)
  - Print shop sound effects, circa 1980 (Box 34, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0031)
  - Sound rolls, 1978-1980 (Box 34, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0030, 002_0032, 002_0034, 002_0035, 002_0036, 002_0037)
  - Trims and outs, circa 1980 (Box 17, 16mm film reels 002_0010, 002_0011, 002_0012, 002_0013, 002_0014, 002_0015, 002_0016, 002_0017, 002_0018, 002_0019, 002_0020, 002_0021, 002_0022, 002_0023, 16mm film reels 002_0024, 002_0025, 002_0026, 002_0027, 002_0028, 002_0049, 002_0058, 002_0059, 002_0060, 002_0061, 002_0062, 002_0063, 002_0064, 002_0065)
- Series II. Planet Without a Visa, 2 Linear Feet in two record cartons; 23 sound tape reels; 4 film reels
  Series II. Planet Without a Visa contains sound elements and reference materials for the unfinished documentary film by David Loeb Weiss. Reference materials include recordings from a University of Mexico Colloquium on Trotsky, a lecture on Trotsky by Jean Van Hevenoort, an interview with Galina Ivanovna, and a film on James P. Cannon.
  - J. P. Cannon Roll 3 Part 2, Undated; cuid212 (Box 30, Film 1)
  - Jean Van Hevenoort Lecture on Trotsky, Harvard University, January 7, 1980 (Box 29, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0044)
  - LDT-R1 'Traitor' Cannon, Undated; cuid209 (Box 27, 16mm film reels 1)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Duration: 9 min. 22 sec., Color, Silent; Preservation note: "B-wind double-perf color reversal. Ektachrome EF stock with 1972 date code. Slight edgewave; soundtrack is not available."
  - LDT-R2 'Traitor' Cannon, Nick Castle, Undated; cuid210 (Box 27, 16mm film reels 2)
    Duration: 11 min. 39 sec., Color, Silent; Preservation note: "B-wind double-perf color reversal. Ektachrome EF stock with 1972 date code; soundtrack element is not available."
  - LDT-R3 'Traitor' Cannon, Undated; cuid211 (Box 27, 16mm film reels 3)
    Duration: 11 min. 37 sec., Color, Silent; Preservation note: "B-wind double-perf color reversal. Ektachrome EF stock with 1972 date code. Edgewave; soundtrack element is unavailable."
  - Pre-Interview with Galina Ivanovna, Undated (Box 29, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0053)
  - Pre-Production Trial, November 1, 1990 (Box 29, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0054)
  - Sound -- 1, Undated (Box 29, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0051)
  - Sound -- 2, 5, 6, 7, part of 8, Undated (Box 29, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0055)
  - Sound -- 3, end of 8, 9, 10, Undated (Box 29, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0052)
  - Univeristy of Mexico Trotsky Colloquium Tape 2 -- Adolfo Gilly, May 18, 1987 (Box 29, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0046)
  - Univeristy of Mexico Trotsky Colloquium Tape 3 -- Adolfo Gilly, May 18, 1987 (Box 29, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0047)
  - Univeristy of Mexico Trotsky Colloquium Tape 4 -- Pierre Broué, May 18, 1987 (Box 29, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0038)
    The lecture is titled "Leon Trotsky a 20 años de Octubre."
  - Univeristy of Mexico Trotsky Colloquium Tape 5 -- Enrique Avilar, May 19, 1987 (Box 29, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0039)
    The lecture is titled "Mexico, el unico visado en el planeta para Trotsky."
  - Univeristy of Mexico Trotsky Colloquium Tape 6 -- Pierre Broué, May 19, 1987 (Box 29, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0040)
    The lecture is titled "Contraprocesso de la Comision Dewey"
  - Univeristy of Mexico Trotsky Colloquium Tape 7 -- Pierre Broué and Peter Katel, May 19, 1987 (Box 29, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0041)
    Broué's lecture is titled "Contraprocesso de la Comision Dewey"; Katel lectures on the U.S. press.
  - Univeristy of Mexico Trotsky Colloquium Tape 8 -- Peter Katel, Ricardo Perez Montfort, May 19, 1987 (Box 29, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0056)
    Katel lectures on the U.S. press; Perez Montfort lectures on the Mexican right.
  - Univeristy of Mexico Trotsky Colloquium Tape 9 -- Teresa Aguirre, May 20, 1987 (Box 29, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0057)
    This lecture is titled "Lombardo contra Trotsky."
  - Univeristy of Mexico Trotsky Colloquium Tape 10 -- Teresa Aguirre, May 20, 1987 (Box 29, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0050)
  - Univeristy of Mexico Trotsky Colloquium Tape 11 -- Felix Ibarra and Octavio Fernandez, May 20, 1987 (Box 28, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0068)
    Lecture titles include "Primeros Pasos del Trotskysmo en Mexico," "Nacimiento de la Oposicion de Izquierda en Mexico" by Felix Ibarra, and "Trotsky y los Trotskystos Mexicanos" by Octavio Fernandez.
  - Univeristy of Mexico Trotsky Colloquium Tape 12 -- Octavio Fernandez, May 20, 1987 (Box 28, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0067)
  - Univeristy of Mexico Trotsky Colloquium Tape 13 -- Octavio Fernandez, May 20, 1987 (Box 28, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0066)
  - Univeristy of Mexico Trotsky Colloquium Tape 14 -- Manuel Aguilar Mora, May 21, 1987 (Box 28, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0069)
    Lecture titles include "Ideas, Artes, Ideologias, ¿Una Triple Militencia?" and "Sigueros Contra Trotsky" by Manuel Aguilar Mora.
  - Univeristy of Mexico Trotsky Colloquium Tape 17 -- Adolfo Gilly, 1987 (Box 29, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0042)
  - Univeristy of Mexico Trotsky Colloquium Tape 18 -- David's Introductory Remarks, Interviews with Young People, 1987 (Box 29, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0043)
  - University of Mexico Trotsky Colloquium -- Pierre Broué (end of speech), May 18, 1987 (Box 29, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0048)
  - University of Mexico Trotsky Colloquium -- Wednesday Main Sessions, May 20, 1987 (Box 29, Quarter inch audio reel 002_0045)
    Sessions listed include: "Greetings from Canada - Al Capp, Letter from Germany, Greetings from the Ligue Communiste, Organizational report, Financial report, Organizer report, Telegram - Seattle 8, Discussion on above, Telegram to Steve Warshell, Discussion continued, Greetings from Italy, Summary of Org. report, Telegram to Mexican Political Prisoners, Arab Panel"